Good evening. My name is Chris Val
Hilditch. I'm deputy director of public
works for the city of Lancaster for
utilities. With me is my c-orker, Ben
Perwin. He's a senior project manager in
our water bureau.
This evening, we're here to present the
environmental review for our phase 2 and
phase 3 large diameter transmission
mate. We will go over the permitting
that's been involved in this project and
we'll talk about why there's a public
meeting about this under the national
environmental policy and we'll also
review the timeline of the project.
So, what is the phase two and three
large iron transmission main project? A
little bit of a backstory in the way
that the city actually produces water.
The city of Lancaster owns, operates,
and maintains a portable water system
that provides water to over 120,000
people in Lancaster County.
The system is supplied from two water
treatment plants. One that is fed from
the Knesogga River and one that is read
from the Sescuana River.
The Sesuana treatment plant was built in
the 1950s.
And while the treatment plant and
pumping infrastructure have all been
upgraded,
the pipes going from the river intake to
the treatment plant and then from the
treatment plant and then the finished
water from the treatment plant to the
reservoir
and then into the city were not touched.
In 2012, there was a leak on this line
and it cost about $200,000 to fix.
The city was able to keep water flowing
throughout this time. However, it was a
little bit of wakeup call to us that
says that we needed better
infrastructure so that this wouldn't be
an issue in the future.
A study came out of this and
laid the groundwork for this project. I
have been involved in the I have been
with the city for about 12 years and
this project has been with me this
entire 12 years. The study came out in
2020 in 2013 and we've been working on
it ever since. In 2022,
the city finished phase one of the large
dime transmission main which completed
the main which completed a redundant
main from the treatment from our oyster
point reservoir into the city.
So, this would just be finishing
that project and adding a redundant line
to the main that was installed in 1955.
This map shows the proposed route of the
water main that is proposed.
The orange line is the phase three large
diameter transmission main and that is
the raw water line from the river to the
treatment plant.
Phase two is the treated water that goes
from the treatment plant up to our
Oyster Point reservoir.
Um you can see in Mount Bill there is a
um line that goes up. This provides an
interconnect to one of our um to one of
our other distribution mains and it
allows the city's distribution network
to have full redundancy.
This main runs through Columbia Burrow,
West Hempfield, Mount Vill Burrow, and
into East Hempfield.
These are some of the just the required
permits that we were that we needed to
get for this project. There are many
different um acronym organizations that
were used that provide these permits.
The first two permits are from the PA
ADP, safe drinking water bureau.
They have one for the raw water phase
and one for the finished water phase.
This main also crosses two different
railroads, one being Norfolk Southern
and the other one being the Columbia and
Reading Railroad.
There's a pen dot highway occupancy
permit that's required because some of
this main goes along um Columbia Avenue
and Route 462.
And then there's many other local road
permits that we would need to get.
NPDS permit is stands for the national
balloon discharge and it is required for
when you're disturbing the earth
and so that we don't have any issues
with the environment while we're doing
the
construction of this. And then the last
permit is the joint permit for the
stream crossings.
These are joint responsibility between
the PA ADP and the Army Corps and the
Army Corps of Engineers.
All these permits have been applied for
and we're working on getting them and
we're working through comments
currently.
So why is there a public meeting about
this this evening? Our project cost for
the project is estimated between 40 and
15 million and this includes
approximately 1.25 million of design and
surveying services.
The city applied to the Commonwealth
Finance Authority for ARPA funding in
2023 for the full cost of both projects,
both phase 2 and phase three, but only
received 3,132,000
for phase 2. There was significant
competition for the ARPA funding
throughout the entire state of
Pennsylvania.
We we are applying for PENvest funding.
Penvest is a gives us low interest loans
to utilities in the Commonwealth. And
one of the requirements that they have
is that they require that any major
project have an environmental study
under the National Environmental Policy.
And you'll hear the acronym NEPA.
NEPA establishes the National Charter
for Environmental Protection. It
requires the identification of
environmental consequences and
mitigation measures. So even though we
have multiple permits that we've applied
for because of those permits
specifically some of our project will be
in the flood plane and that's
unavoidable because we have to withdraw
water from the Susuana River. So we're
in the flood plane being adjacent to the
river and as Ben pointed out we have
several stream crossings to get the
water throughout the distribution
system. Under this environmental policy,
there's three different tiers of
environmental review. The first one
being a categorical exclusion,
an environmental assessment, and then a
very fullscale project review and
environmental impact statement. The EIS
was not required for this project. The
city had applied for the categorical
exclusion, but a D had ruled that we
were not allowed to do that because of
the creek crossings and the and the
flood plane impact.
So the categorical exclusion is only
used for projects with no significant
impact. And again, as I said, the
project was not eligible because of the
creek crossings and the flood plate.
Some examples of eligible projects that
we've been successful with in the past.
Inflow and infiltration, correction, and
wastewater systems, cleaning and lining
of drinking water pipes, repair of
existing equipment. These are types of
projects where we we would not be
disturbing anything in the environment.
An example of those where we are
disturbing might be new or relocated
wastewater discharges
intakes or substantial increases in
discharge fall.
So where we ended up falling was under
the environmental assessment.
So this is the next stage for projects
not eligible for a categorical
exclusion. So since we were not
eligible, we started under this path. We
are utilizing a process called the
uniform environmental process or UER and
this is what was required by the pad and
penbes. The city hired Aero Engineering
to do an environmental assessment. The
plans are now completed and they're
working through the narratives now with
the in preparation for filing with the
D.
One of the requirements is that we have
the ability to talk about our project
before the public. So, we're on YouTube
this evening to allow the public to
understand this project and to ask
questions in the future. So, this is why
we're here this evening.
So, a little background as to the
timeline of this of this project. So, we
are applying to these PENvest funds in
July of 2025.
This in September of 2025, we should be
receiving all of the permits required
for we should be finished receiving all
the permits required for this project.
In October 2025, we should be receiving
the Penvest funding approval.
And then in October and November with
Penvest on board, we should be bidding
construction and buying the pipe. And
hopefully we'll be con and hopefully
that would come up with a start date of
construction of January 2026
with construction being completed in
about 15 months or March of 2027.
So if you wish to receive any additional
information on this project on the
YouTube channel, we'll be posting our
emails for review for your review. Thank
you for your attention this evening and
we'll be starting this project shortly.